So, I've known a lot of fish in my life.
لقد تعرفت على الكثير من الأسماك في حياتي ..
I've loved only two.
ولكنني أحببت فقط إثنتين
That first one,
هذه هي الأولى ..
it was more like a passionate affair.
لقد كانت أكثر من علاقة عاطفية .
It was a beautiful fish:
لقد كانت سمكة جميلة
flavorful, textured, meaty,
لذيذة , مزخرفة , غنية باللحم
a bestseller on the menu.
أفضل ما يمكن بيعه من على قائمة الطعام
What a fish.
يا لها من سمكة .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Even better,
بل و أكثر
it was farm-raised to the supposed highest standards
لقد تم تربيتها في مزارع السمك بأعلى المعاير المطلوبة
of sustainability.
للإستدامة
So you could feel good about selling it.
مما يجعلك تشعر بصورة جيدة عند بيعها .
I was in a relationship with this beauty
ولقد كنت في علاقة مع هذه الجميلة ..
for several months.
لعدة أشهر
One day, the head of the company called
ويوما ما , اتصل رئيس الشركة ..
and asked if I'd speak at an event
وسألني إن كان بإمكاني التحدث في مؤتمر
about the farm's sustainability.
عن إستدامة مزرعة الأسماك تلك
"Absolutely," I said.
فأجبت " حتماً "
Here was a company trying to solve
إنها شركة تحاول حل ..
what's become this unimaginable problem for us chefs:
مايعتبر المشكلة الأخطر لطباخيها ..
How do we keep fish on our menus?
وهي كيف نُبقي السمك على لائحة طعامنا المتوفر ؟
For the past 50 years,
لمدة 50 عام المنصرمة
we've been fishing the seas
كنا نصطاد من البحار
like we clear-cut forests.
كما إزالة الاشجار من الغابات
It's hard to overstate the destruction.
ومن الصعب توضيح الدمار الذي حدث
Ninety percent of large fish, the ones we love --
ف 90% من الاسماك الكبيرة , والتي نُحب
the tunas, the halibuts, the salmons, swordfish --
التونا , القفندر , السلمون , سمك سياف البحر
they've collapsed.
دمرت
There's almost nothing left.
ولم يعد منها شيء تقريباً
So, for better or for worse,
وسواء كان هذا إيجابياً أم سلبياً
aquaculture, fish farming, is going to be a part of our future.
فإن الزراعة السمكية ستصبح جزء من مستقبلنا
A lot of arguments against it:
وهنالك الكثير من الأعتراضات ضدها
Fish farms pollute -- most of them do anyway --
فمزارع الأسماك تلوث المحيط .. معظمها يقم بذلك على الأقل
and they're inefficient. Take tuna,
وهي غير فعالة .. لنأخذ التونا على سبيل المثال
a major drawback.
يوجد عيب كبير في مزارعها
It's got a feed conversion ratio
لانها تملك نسبة تغذية
of 15 to one.
15 إلى 1
That means it takes fifteen pounds of wild fish
أي أنك تحتاج إطعامها 15 باوندا من السمك الحر
to get you one pound of farm tuna.
لكي تحصل على 1 باوند من سمك التونة في المزرعة
Not very sustainable.
أي استدامة سيئة
It doesn't taste very good either.
بالإضافة إلى أن مذاقها سيء
So here, finally,
لذا لدينا هنا .. أخيراً !
was a company trying to do it right.
شركة تريد القيام بالامور على النحو الصحيح .
I wanted to support them.
وأردت مساعدتهم
The day before the event,
ففي اليوم الذي يسبق المؤتمر .
I called the head of P.R. for the company.
أتصلت برئيس العلاقات العامة لتلك الشركة .
Let's call him Don.
ولندعوه " دون "
"Don," I said, "just to get the facts straight, you guys are famous
سئلته " دون , فقط لكي أفهم الأمور جيداً , أنتم مشهورون جداً ...
for farming so far out to sea, you don't pollute."
في زراعة الاسماك خارج البحر .. وأنتم لاتلوثون المحيط حتى الآن"
"That's right," he said. "We're so far out,
فأجاب " نعم هذا صحيح نحن كذلك حتى الآن ...
the waste from our fish gets distributed,
فمخلفات الأسماك لدينا توزع ...
not concentrated."
ولا يتم تركيزها "
And then he added,
ثم أضاف ..
"We're basically a world unto ourselves.
" نحن تقريباً عالم مستقبل بذاتنا ..
That feed conversion ratio? 2.5 to one," he said.
ونسبة التغذية لدينا 2.5 الى 1 "
"Best in the business."
" الأفضل في السوق "
2.5 to one, great.
2.5 الى 1 , ممتاز
"2.5 what? What are you feeding?"
من ماذا 2.5 الى 1 ؟ مالذي تطعمونها ؟
"Sustainable proteins," he said.
أجاب " بروتينات مستدامة "
"Great," I said. Got off the phone.
أجبت " ممتاز " وأغلقت الهاتف
And that night, I was lying in bed, and I thought:
وفي تلك الليلة كنت مستلقٍ على السرير وفكرت في نفسي ..
What the hell is a sustainable protein?
" ما هي البروتينات المستدامة بحق الإله ؟ "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
So the next day, just before the event, I called Don.
لذا في اليوم التالي وقبل المؤتمر هاتفت " دون "
I said, "Don, what are some examples of sustainable proteins?"
سئلته " دون , هل يمكنك أعطائي بعض الأمثلة عن البروتينات المستدامة ؟ "
He said he didn't know. He would ask around.
فأجابني أنه لا يعلم . وسوف يسأل عن الأمر
Well, I got on the phone with a few people in the company;
حسناً , بدأت اهاتف بعض الاشخاص في الشركة
no one could give me a straight answer
ولم يستطع أياً منهم أن يعطيني أجابة واضحة
until finally, I got on the phone
حتى في النهاية تم تحويلي الى ..
with the head biologist.
المسؤل البيولوجي
Let's call him Don too.
ولندعوه " دون " أيضاً
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
"Don," I said,
قلت " دون ...
"what are some examples of sustainable proteins?"
أعطني بعض الأمثلة عن البروتينات المستدامة "
Well, he mentioned some algaes
حسناً , لقد عدد لي بعض العوالق ..
and some fish meals,
وبعض أطعمة السمك ..
and then he said chicken pellets.
ومن ثم قال و" كرات الدجاج "
I said, "Chicken pellets?"
تعجبت " كرات الدجاج ؟؟ "
He said, "Yeah, feathers, skin,
قال " نعم فالريش , الجلد ...
bone meal, scraps,
العظام , الزوائد ,
dried and processed into feed."
تجفف وتعالج إلى أطعمة "
I said, "What percentage
فسئلته " كم نسبة ...
of your feed is chicken?"
الدجاج في طعامكم ؟ "
Thinking, you know, two percent.
كنت أعتقد , كما تعلمون , 2%
"Well, it's about 30 percent," he said.
فأجاب " نحو 30% "
I said, "Don, what's sustainable
فقلت " دون , ماهو الامر المستديم ..
about feeding chicken to fish?"
في إطعام الأسماك الدجاج ؟ "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
There was a long pause on the line,
وبعد صمت طويل على الهاتف
and he said, "There's just too much chicken in the world."
قال " يوجد الكثير من الدجاج في العالم !!! "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
I fell out of love with this fish.
لم أعد أحب هذه السمكة .
No, not because I'm some self-righteous,
لا , ليس لانني معتدٌ بنفسي قليلاً
goody-two shoes foodie.
وليس لأنني أقرف سريعاً من الطعام
I actually am.
رغم أنني كذلك
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
No, I actually fell out of love with this fish because, I swear to God,
لا , فقد توقفت عن حب هذه السمكة لانني " أُقسم "
after that conversation, the fish tasted like chicken.
بعد تلك المحادثة بدأت أشعر بطعم الدجاج في تلك السمكة .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
This second fish,
هذه هي السمكة الثانية .
it's a different kind of love story.
ولها قصة حبٍ مختلفة .
It's the romantic kind,
إنها من النوع الرومانسي ,
the kind where the more you get to know your fish,
انها من النوع الذي كلما إزددت معرفة بالسمكة ..
you love the fish.
كلما أحببتها أكثر .
I first ate it at a restaurant
وقد تذوقتها أول مرة في مطعم ,,
in southern Spain.
في جنوب إسبانيا
A journalist friend had been talking about this fish for a long time.
فقد كان ليَّ صديقةٌ صحفية تخبرني عنها طيلة الوقت ..
She kind of set us up.
وقد عرفتنا على بعضنا البعض - أنا والسمكة -
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
It came to the table
وقد جاءت الى طاولة الطعام
a bright, almost shimmering, white color.
براقة , تكاد تومض , بحلة بيضاء
The chef had overcooked it.
وكان طاهي المطعم قد بالغ في طهيها ..
Like twice over.
مرتين أكثر من اللازم
Amazingly, it was still delicious.
ولكن وبصورة مدهشة مازالت لذيذة ..
Who can make a fish taste good
من يمكنه أن يجعل سمكة بهذه اللذة ...
after it's been overcooked?
حتى بعد أن بالغ في طهيها؟
I can't,
أنا لا أستطيع هذا !
but this guy can.
ولكن ذلك الرجل يستطيع .
Let's call him Miguel --
ولندعوه " ميجيل "
actually his name is Miguel.
في الواقع أسمه الحقيقي " ميجيل "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
And no, he didn't cook the fish, and he's not a chef,
ولكنه لم يكن هو الذي طبخ السمكة , حتى إنه ليس طباخاً
at least in the way that you and I understand it.
على الأقل ليس في المعنى الذي نعرفه .
He's a biologist
فهو عالم بيولوجي
at Veta La Palma.
في " فيتا لا بالما "
It's a fish farm in the southwestern corner of Spain.
وهي مزرعة أسماك في جنوب غرب اسبانيا
It's at the tip of the Guadalquivir river.
تقع على طرف نهر " جاوداليجيفر "
Until the 1980s,
حتى 1980 ..
the farm was in the hands of the Argentinians.
كانت هذه المزرعة ملكاً للأرجنتينين
They raised beef cattle
كانوا يربون فيها الماشية ..
on what was essentially wetlands.
على ما كان سابقاً أرضٌ رطبة
They did it by draining the land.
فقد جففوا الأرض
They built this intricate series of canals,
ببناء شبكة من قنوات التصريف
and they pushed water off the land and out into the river.
لتصريف المياه خارجاً من الأرض إلى النهر
Well, they couldn't make it work,
ولكن هذا لم ينجح معهم ..
not economically.
إقتصادياً على الأقل .
And ecologically, it was a disaster.
وقد دمرت النظام البيئي هناك ..
It killed like 90 percent of the birds,
فقد قتل مايقارب 90% من الطيور
which, for this place, is a lot of birds.
وكانت تلك المنطقة مليئة بالطيور ..
And so in 1982,
ولذلك في عام 1982
a Spanish company with an environmental conscience
شركة إسبانية لديها ضمير بيئي ..
purchased the land.
إشترت تلك الارض .
What did they do?
ومالذي فعلوه هناك ؟
They reversed the flow of water.
لقد أعادوا تدفق المياه ..
They literally flipped the switch.
فقد عكسوا " حرفياً " عنفة المجرى .
Instead of pushing water out,
وبدلاً من إخراج المياه خارجاً
they used the channels to pull water back in.
فقد إستخدموا الشبكة لإعادة المياه
They flooded the canals.
فغمروا القنوات بالمياه
They created a 27,000-acre fish farm --
ونتج عن ذلك 27000 فدان من مزارع السمك
bass, mullet,
البص , البوري ..
shrimp, eel --
والجمبري .. إلخ
and in the process, Miguel and this company
وضمن تلك العملية " ميجيل " وشركته
completely reversed the ecological destruction.
إستطاعوا إعادة إحياء النظام البيئي بعد تدميره
The farm's incredible.
إنها مزرعة أسماك رائعة
I mean, you've never seen anything like this.
أعني أنك لن ترى مثلها مثيل ..
You stare out at a horizon
فأنت تحدق في الأفق
that is a million miles away,
في مليون ميل إلى الأمام
and all you see are flooded canals
وكل الذي تراه هو القنوات المغمورة بالمياه
and this thick, rich marshland.
والمستنقعات الكثيفة والغنية
I was there not long ago with Miguel.
لقد كنت هنالك مع " ميجيل " منذ وقت قريب
He's an amazing guy,
وهو رجلٌ رائع جداً
like three parts Charles Darwin and one part Crocodile Dundee.
ثلاثة أرباعه " شارلز داروين " والربع المتبقي " التمساح دندي "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Okay? There we are slogging through the wetlands,
حسناً . نحن الآن نتجول في الأرض الرطبة ..
and I'm panting and sweating, got mud up to my knees,
وأنا ألهث واتعرق والطين وصل الى ركبتي ..
and Miguel's calmly conducting a biology lecture.
و " ميجيل " يُلقي عليَّ محاضرة بعلوم الأحياء بكل هدوء ..
Here, he's pointing out a rare Black-shouldered Kite.
وهاهو , يشير الى نوع نادر من طير الكتف الاسود
Now, he's mentioning the mineral needs of phytoplankton.
وهنا يعدد الإحتياجات المعدينة للعوالق النباتية
And here, here he sees a grouping pattern
وهنا , هنا يرى تجمع ما ...
that reminds him of the Tanzanian Giraffe.
يذكره بالزرافات التنزانية
It turns out, Miguel spent the better part of his career
فقد تبين لي أن " ميجيل " قضى أفضل أوقات مسيرته العملية ..
in the Mikumi National Park in Africa.
في حديقة " ميكاموي " الوطنية في أفريقيا
I asked him how he became
فسئلته كيف غدا ..
such an expert on fish.
خبيراً في الاسماك هكذا ..
He said, "Fish? I didn't know anything about fish.
فأجاب " السمك ؟؟ أنا لا أعرف شيئاً عنها ! ..
I'm an expert in relationships."
انا خبيرٌ في العلاقات "
And then he's off, launching into more talk
ثم أنطلق يُكمل حديثه عن ..
about rare birds and algaes
بعض الطيور النادرة والعوالق ..
and strange aquatic plants.
والنباتات المائية الغريبة ..
And don't get me wrong, that was really fascinating, you know,
ولاتفهموني بصورة خاطئة .. فقد كان ذلك مذهلاً - كما تعلمون -
the biotic community unplugged, kind of thing.
شيءٌ كما مجتمع حيوي كامل بدون أي قيود ..
It's great, but I was in love.
شيءٌ رائع .. ولكني كنت واقعاً في الحب
And my head was swooning over that
وكان عقلي منتشياً بتلك ..
overcooked piece of delicious fish I had the night before.
القطعة الشهية من السمك التي أكلت في الليلة السابقة
So I interrupted him. I said,
فقاطعته قائلا ..
"Miguel, what makes your fish taste so good?"
" ميجيل , مالذي يجعل أسماكك ذات مذاق رائع ؟ "
He pointed at the algae.
فأشار الى العوالق النباتية .
"I know, dude, the algae, the phytoplankton,
" أعلم يا رجل هذا , العوالق , العوالق النباتية ..
the relationships: It's amazing.
العلاقات , انها رائعة . ...
But what are your fish eating?
ولكن مالذي تأكله أسماكك ؟
What's the feed conversion ratio?"
ماهي نسبة التغذية لديكم ؟ "
Well, he goes on to tell me
حسناً , أكمل قوله ..
it's such a rich system
أن نظامهم هذا غنيٌ جداً
that the fish are eating what they'd be eating in the wild.
حيث أن السمك يأكلون ما يؤكل في حياتهم البحرية ..
The plant biomass, the phytoplankton,
أي أجزاء نباتية , عوالق نباتية ..
the zooplankton, it's what feeds the fish.
عوالق حيوانية . إنه ما تأكله الأسماك ..
The system is so healthy,
النظام صحيٌ جداً
it's totally self-renewing.
وهو متجددٌ تماماً بصورة ذاتية
There is no feed.
لذا لانحتاج لإطعامه شيئاً
Ever heard of a farm that doesn't feed its animals?
هل سمعتم من قبل بمزرعة لاتطعم حيواناتها ؟
Later that day, I was driving around this property with Miguel,
ثم في ذلك اليوم لاحقاً , كنت أقود سيارتي حول المنشأة مع " ميجيل "
and I asked him, I said, "For a place that seems so natural,
فسئلته " بالنسبة لمكان يبدو طبيعي هكذا "
unlike like any farm I'd ever been at,
ليس كمثل أي مزرعة رأيت من قبل ,
how do you measure success?"
" كيف تقيس مدى نجاحك ؟ "
At that moment, it was as if
كانت تلك اللحظة كما يحدث ..
a film director called for a set change.
مع المخرج السينمائي حين يطلب تغير موقع التصوير ..
And we rounded the corner
حيث كنا ندور على منعطف ..
and saw the most amazing sight:
ورأيت أجمل مشهد ..
thousands and thousands of pink flamingos,
لألآف وألآف من طيور النحام الزهرية
a literal pink carpet for as far as you could see.
منبسطة على مدى البصر كنسيج زهري
"That's success," he said.
فقال " هذا هو النجاح "
"Look at their bellies, pink.
" أنظر الى بطونها , انها زهرية ..
They're feasting."
انها مليئة بالفرائس "
Feasting? I was totally confused.
فرائس ؟؟ " لقد أصبت بالتشويش
I said, "Miguel, aren't they feasting on your fish?"
وقلت " ميجيل , أليست هذه الفرائس هي أسماكك ؟؟ "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
"Yes," he said.
وأجاب " نعم "
"We lose 20 percent of our fish
" نحن نخسر 20% من أسماكنا ...
and fish eggs to birds.
وبيوض الأسماك للطيور "
Well, last year, this property
حسناً , السنة السابقة هذه المنشأة
had 600,000 birds on it,
إحتضنت 600000 طير
more than 250 different species.
مايقارب 250 نوعاً مختلفاً منها
It's become, today, the largest
وقد غدت اليوم , أكبر
and one of the most important
وواحدة من أهم
private bird sanctuaries in all of Europe."
المحميات الخاصة في كل أوروبا "
I said, "Miguel, isn't a thriving bird population
فقلت " ميجيل , أليس تجمع مزدهر من الطيور ..
like the last thing you want on a fish farm?"
هو أسوء شيء قد يحدث لمزرعة أسماك ؟ "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
He shook his head, no.
فحرك رأسه وقال " لا "
He said, "We farm extensively,
وأضاف " نحن نزرع بشكل منتشر ..
not intensively.
وليس بشكل مكثف .
This is an ecological network.
هذه شبكة نظام حيوي متكامل ...
The flamingos eat the shrimp.
حيث يأكل طير النحام الجمبري
The shrimp eat the phytoplankton.
ويأكل الجمبري العوالق النباتية
So the pinker the belly,
لذا فكلما كانت بطون الطيور زهرية أكثر ..
the better the system."
كلما كان النظام يعمل بصورة أفضل "
Okay, so let's review:
حسناً لنراجع هذا ..
a farm that doesn't feed its animals,
مزرعة لا تطعم حيواناتها ,
and a farm that measures its success
ومزرعة تقيس مستوى نجاحها ..
on the health of its predators.
نسبةً إلى صحة مفترسي حيواناتها .
A fish farm, but also a bird sanctuary.
مزرعة أسماك ولكن في نفس الوقت محمية طيور .
Oh, and by the way, those flamingos,
آه , بالمناسبة , طيور النحام تلك ..
they shouldn't even be there in the first place.
لا يجب أن تكون هنا في الأصل .
They brood in a town
فهي تُعشعش في مدينة ..
150 miles away,
على بعد 150 ميلاً
where the soil conditions
حيث ظروف التربة هناك ..
are better for building nests.
أفضل لبناء الأعشاش .
Every morning, they fly
وكل صباح تطير ..
150 miles into the farm.
150 ميلاً إلى المزرعة ..
And every evening, they fly 150 miles back.
وفي كل مساء تطير 150 ميلاً لكي تعود
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
They do that because they're able to follow
وهي قادرة على ذلك لانها تتبع ..
the broken white line
الخط المتقطع ..
of highway A92.
للطريق السريع ( A92 )
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
No kidding.
نعم حقاً
I was imagining a "March of the Penguins" thing,
وكنت أتخيل في نفس الوقت مسيرة لطيور البطريق ..
so I looked at Miguel.
ونظرت إلى " ميجيل "
I said, "Miguel, do they fly
وقلت " ميجيل " هل فعلاً تطير تلك الطيور
150 miles to the farm,
150 ميلاً الى المزرعة
and then do they fly
ومن ثم تطير ..
150 miles back at night?
150 ميلاً أخرى لكي تعود ؟
Do they do that for the children?"
هل تفعل ذلك من أجل فراخها ؟
He looked at me like I had just quoted a Whitney Houston song.
نظر إلي كما لو أنني أقتبست جملة من أغنية " ويتني هيوستن "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
He said, "No; they do it because the food's better."
وقال " لا ... بل إنها تفعل ذلك لأن الطعام هنا أفضل "
I didn't mention the skin of my beloved fish,
نسيت أن أخبركم عن جلد سمكتي المحبوبة ,
which was delicious -- and I don't like fish skin;
والتي كانت لذيذة جداً , أنا لا أحب جلد السمك ..
I don't like it seared, I don't like it crispy.
لا أحبه سواء كان مقمراً أو حاراً مقرمشاً ..
It's that acrid, tar-like flavor.
انه صلب وطعمه كنكهة الإسفلت .. !
I almost never cook with it.
وعادة لا أطبخه - جلد السمك -
Yet, when I tasted it at that restaurant in southern Spain,
ولكن عندما جربته في ذلك المطعم في جنوب إسبانيا ..
it tasted not at all like fish skin.
لم يكن طعمه كجلد السمك على الإطلاق
It tasted sweet and clean,
فقد كان مذاقه " نظيفاً وناعماً "
like you were taking a bite of the ocean.
كما لو أنك تأكل قضمة من المحيط
I mentioned that to Miguel, and he nodded.
فذكرت ذلك لميجيل , فأومأ برأسه
He said, "The skin acts like a sponge.
وقال " إن جلد السمك مثل الإسفنج .
It's the last defense before anything enters the body.
كما أنه خط الدفاع الأول قبل أن يخترق أي شيء الجسد
It evolved to soak up impurities."
وقد تطور لكي يمتص الملوثات "
And then he added,
ومن ثم أضاف
"But our water has no impurities."
" ولكنه لا يوجد لدينا ملوثات "
OK. A farm that doesn't feed its fish,
حسناً , مزرعة لا تطعم أسماكها ..
a farm that measures its success
ومزرعة تقيس نجاحها ..
by the success of its predators.
على مدى نجاح مفترسي أسماكها
And then I realized when he says,
ومن ثم أدركت عندما قال ,
"A farm that has no impurities,"
أنها مزرعة بدون ملوثات ,
he made a big understatement,
وحصل لدي سوء فهم كبير هنا ..
because the water that flows through that farm
لان الماء الذي يُساق إلى المزرعة
comes in from the Guadalquivir River.
قادم من نهر " جواداليجيفير "
It's a river that carries with it
إنه النهر الذي يحمل معه ..
all the things that rivers tend to carry these days:
كل تلك الاشياء التي يحملها الأنهار هذه الأيام
chemical contaminants,
ملوثات كيميائية
pesticide runoff.
ومخلفات المبيدات
And when it works its way through the system
وعندما تعبر المياه هذا النظام ..
and leaves,
وتتركه
the water is cleaner than when it entered.
تخرج بصورة أكثر نقاءا مما دخلت به ..
The system is so healthy, it purifies the water.
فهذا النظام صحيٌ جداً لدرجة أنه ينقي المياه
So, not just a farm that doesn't feed its animals,
إذا ليس فقط انها لا تطعم أسماكها
not just a farm that measures its success
وليس فقط أنها تقيس نجاحها ..
by the health of its predators,
بواسطة نجاح مفترسي أسماكها
but a farm that's literally a water purification plant --
أنما أيضاً مزرعة تعمل " حرفيا " كمصنع تنقية مياه
and not just for those fish,
ليس فقط للأسماك ..
but for you and me as well.
إنما لي ولك على حدً سواء
Because when that water leaves, it dumps out into the Atlantic.
لان مياه المزرعة عندما تغادر فإنها تغادر المحيط الاطلنطي
A drop in the ocean, I know,
ترمى في المحيط , نعم أعلم .
but I'll take it, and so should you,
لكنها ستصل إلي وستصل إليك كذلك
because this love story,
لان قصة الحب هذه ..
however romantic,
بقدر ما فيها من رومانسية
is also instructive.
فيها ايضاً الفائدة
You might say it's a recipe
ويمكنك القول عنها أنها وصفة
for the future of good food,
لمستقبل الطعام الصحي .
whether we're talking about bass or beef cattle.
سواء كنا نتحدث عن سمك " الباس " أو لحم الماشية
What we need now is
فالذي نحتاج إليه اليوم ..
a radically new conception of agriculture,
مفهوم جديدٌ جذرياً للزراعة
one in which the food actually tastes good.
نظام يكون فيه طعم الطعام جيدٌ فعلاً
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
But for a lot people,
ولكن لكثير من الناس ..
that's a bit too radical.
فهذا جذريٌ جداً
We're not realists, us foodies;
فنحن لسنا واقعيون - نحن متذوقي الأطعمة -
we're lovers.
لأننا عشاق
We love farmers' markets,
فنحن نحب أسواق المزراع
we love small family farms,
ونحب المزارع العائلية الصغيرة
we talk about local food,
ونتحدث عن الطعام المحلي
we eat organic.
ونأكل الأطعمة العضوية
And when you suggest these are the things
وعندما تقترح أن هذه الاشياء
that will ensure the future of good food,
هي التي ستؤمن غذاء المستقبل الصحي
someone, somewhere stands up and says,
فسيظهر أحدهم ليقول
"Hey guy, I love pink flamingos,
" اسمع يا صاح , انا احب طير النحام الزهري
but how are you going to feed the world?"
ولكن كيف ستطعم العالم ؟
How are you going to feed the world?
كيف ستقوم بإطعام العالم ؟
Can I be honest?
هل يمكن أن أكون صريحاً ؟
I don't love that question.
أنا لا أحب هذا السؤال .
No, not because we already produce
لا , ليس لاننا في الأصل ننتج ..
enough calories to more than feed the world.
مايكفي من الوحدات الحرارية لإطعام العالم .
One billion people will go hungry today.
لأن 1 مليار شخص سيباتون جوعى اليوم .
One billion -- that's more than ever before --
1 مليار - أكبر من أي رقم سابق للجوعى -
because of gross inequalities in distribution,
بسبب التفاوت الصارخ في توزيع الأغذية
not tonnage.
وليس بسبب الكمية .
Now, I don't love this question because it's determined the logic
والآن أنا لا احب هذا السؤال لانه يحدد المنطق
of our food system for the last 50 years.
الذي يقوم عليه نظام غذائنا لمدة ال50 عام المنصرمة
Feed grain to herbivores,
فنحن نطعم الحبوب للحيوانات العاشبة ..
pesticides to monocultures, chemicals to soil,
والمبيدات الحشرية للمحاصيل , والكيميائيات للتربة
chicken to fish,
والدجاج للأسماك ,
and all along agribusiness
وعلى جميع الأصعدة الزراعية
has simply asked,
يُطرح سؤالٌ بسيط
"If we're feeding more people more cheaply,
" اذا كان بالأمكان إطعام أُناسٌ أكثر بسعر أقل
how terrible could that be?"
فأي ضرر من هذا سيأتي ؟ "
That's been the motivation,
لقد كان هذا الدافع ..
it's been the justification:
وكان هذا المُشرع لكل ما سبق .
it's been the business plan
إنها خطة عمل
of American agriculture.
للزراعة الأمريكية
We should call it what it is:
ويجب علينا أن نسميها بإسمها الحقيقي
a business in liquidation,
انها خطة للتصفية
a business that's quickly eroding
خطة تؤدي الى تآكل سريع
ecological capital that makes that very production possible.
للنظام البيئي المتكامل الذي يجعل الانتاج الكثيف ذاك مُمكناً
That's not a business,
إن هذا ليس عملاً
and it isn't agriculture.
وهذه ليست زراعة
Our breadbasket is threatened today,
فسلة غذائنا اليوم مهددة
not because of diminishing supply,
ليس بسبب إنخفاض العرض من الغذاء
but because of diminishing resources.
انما بسبب إنخفاض المصادر
Not by the latest combine and tractor invention,
وليس بسبب آخر اختراع للمولد او للجرار
but by fertile land;
انما بسبب خصوبة التربة
not by pumps, but by fresh water;
وليس بسبب المضخات انما بسبب المياه النقية
not by chainsaws, but by forests;
وليس بسبب المناشير انما بسبب الغابات
and not by fishing boats and nets, but by fish in the sea.
وليس بسبب شبكات وقوارب الصيد انما بسبب السمك الحر في البحر
Want to feed the world?
هل تريدون إطعام العالم ؟
Let's start by asking: How are we going to feed ourselves?
لنسأل أنفسنا أولا : كيف سنقوم بإطعام أنفسنا ؟
Or better: How can we create conditions
أو أفضل من هذا , كيف يمكننا صنع ظروفاً ..
that enable every community
تُمكن كل مجتمع ..
to feed itself?
من إطعام نفسه بنفسه
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
To do that,
لنقم بذلك ..
don't look at the agribusiness model for the future.
علينا أن لاننظر الى النماذج الزراعية الحديثة
It's really old, and it's tired.
لانها فعلاً قديمة , ومتعبة
It's high on capital, chemistry and machines,
فهي مُكلفة ومليئة بالكيمياويات والمعدات الصناعية
and it's never produced anything really good to eat.
ولاتنتج على الإطلاق طعاما طعمه جيد
Instead, let's look to the ecological model.
ولكن بدلاً من ذلك علينا ان ننظر الى النموذج البيئي
That's the one that relies on two billion years
وهو النظام الذي يعتمد على خبرة عملية عمرها ..
of on-the-job experience.
2 مليار سنة
Look to Miguel,
لننظر الى " ميجيل "
farmers like Miguel.
المزارعين مثل " ميجيل "
Farms that aren't worlds unto themselves;
المزراع ليست منعزلة بنفسها عن العالم ,
farms that restore instead of deplete;
مزارع تجدد لا تستنزف
farms that farm extensively
مزارع تزرع على مبدأ النشر والتوزيع
instead of just intensively;
لا على مبدأ التكثيف
farmers that are not just producers,
مزارعون ليسوا فقط منتجين ..
but experts in relationships.
إنما أيضاً خبراء في العلاقات
Because they're the ones
لانهم هم نفسهم الأشخاص ...
that are experts in flavor, too.
الخبراء في الطعم أيضاً
And if I'm going to be really honest,
وإذا أردت أن اكون صريحاً
they're a better chef than I'll ever be.
فهم طهاةٌ أفضل مما يمكن أن أصل إليه يوماً
You know, I'm okay with that,
وكما تعلمون , فأنا مرتاح لهذا ..
because if that's the future of good food, it's going to be delicious.
لانه إن كان هذا هو طعام المستقبل فسوف يكون طعاماً شهياً
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
( تصفيق )